<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>single-cell | MLO Lab</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/tag/single-cell/</link><atom:link href="https://mlo-lab.github.io/tag/single-cell/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>single-cell</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2025 MLO Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:36:09 +0200</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://mlo-lab.github.io/media/logo_huedbb8239ffd36c55e33765ff7c80fb90_78702_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url><title>single-cell</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/tag/single-cell/</link></image><item><title>Integrative Analysis of Single-cell Data in Oncology</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/single-cell/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:36:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/single-cell/</guid><description>&lt;p>Single-cell multi-omics data present unique challenges: extreme sparsity and technical noise from dropouts, high dimensionality with thousands of features per cell, and pervasive batch and donor effects that can obscure true biological variation. Robust normalization, dimensionality reduction, and noise-modeling approaches are therefore essential to recover reliable signals and ensure that downstream analyses reflect genuine cellular heterogeneity rather than artifacts of the technology. Our lab combines advanced computational methods with high-dimensional biological data to uncover mechanisms of disease, with a particular emphasis on cancer and metabolic disorders. By integrating single-cell multi-omics, and in vivo model data, we aim to build a mechanistic and spatially resolved understanding of disease progression and therapeutic response.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="single-cell-multi-omics-in-clinical-cohorts">Single-Cell Multi-Omics in Clinical Cohorts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We specialize in the analysis of clinical single-cell multi-omics datasets, particularly from cancer and metabolic disease cohorts. Using state-of-the-art machine learning techniques, we analyze single-cell RNA sequencing and chromatin accessibility data to characterize cellular heterogeneity and regulatory dynamics. Our pipeline includes robust dimensionality reduction, clustering, and batch correction methods, allowing us to identify distinct cell populations and states across individuals. Through probabilistic graphical modeling and motif enrichment analysis, we reconstruct gene regulatory networks that govern disease-specific transcriptional programs. These approaches allow us to overcome the sparsity and noise inherent to single-cell data and extract biologically meaningful patterns that inform prognosis and therapeutic strategy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="multi-omics-in-mouse-models-of-cancer">Multi-Omics in Mouse Models of Cancer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To explore tumor development and treatment effects in vivo, we analyze multi-omics data generated from mouse models, including xenografts and genetically induced cancers. These datasets are complex, encompassing multiple axes of variation such as treatment regimens, time points, and tumor subtypes. To disentangle these factors, we develop tailored probabilistic latent variable models (LVMs) that reveal how sources of variability interact and which molecular features are relevant to human disease. This framework enables us to translate findings from experimental models into clinically actionable insights.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantitative Imaging in Oncology</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/medical-imaging/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:36:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/medical-imaging/</guid><description>&lt;p>High-dimensional imaging datasets pose significant challenges in quantification and interpretation, as traditional analyses often lose critical spatial context and suffer from variability across samples. Our lab applies quantitative imaging, from multiplex confocal microscopy to imaging flow cytometry, to convert biological images into precise, spatially resolved measurements that retain each cell’s location, phenotype, and interactions. We’ve developed colocatome frameworks to map and quantify in situ cellular organization, revealing how microenvironments regulate cell behavior. In parallel, we extract reproducible radiomic features (texture, intensity, shape) and qMRI metrics (e.g., relaxation times) from MRI scans and deploy interpretable machine-learning models to link these imaging biomarkers to clinical outcomes, enabling precise tumor localization and non-invasive monitoring of disease progression.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="quantitative-imaging-and-spatial-analysis">Quantitative Imaging and Spatial Analysis&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We apply quantitative imaging to transform biological images into measurable, interpretable data. From advanced multiplex platforms such as confocal microscopy and imaging flow cytometry, we obtain high-dimensional spatial and phenotypic profiles of cells in their native tissue context. Unlike bulk or sequencing-based approaches, this imaging allows us to retain crucial information on cell location, identity, and interaction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A major component of our spatial analysis pipeline is the development of colocatome frameworks, which quantify the organization and interaction of cell populations in situ. For example, we investigate the spatial positioning of hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) within bone marrow niches using high-resolution microscopy. Understanding these spatial relationships is essential for revealing how microenvironments regulate stem cell behavior and lineage commitment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="radiomics-and-quantitative-mri">Radiomics and Quantitative MRI&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Our imaging research also includes radiological data analysis, with a focus on transitioning from qualitative interpretation to quantitative, reproducible metrics. In radiomics, we extract features such as texture, intensity, and shape from defined regions of interest within MRI scans, and use machine learning models to link these features to clinical outcomes. We emphasize interpretability and robustness, testing models on controlled environments to avoid confounding due to real-patient variability and ethical exposure limitations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In parallel, we employ quantitative MRI (qMRI) techniques to move beyond traditional contrast-based imaging. By measuring intrinsic physical properties of tissues, e.g. relaxation times, we obtain microstructural insights into tissue composition, particularly in brain imaging. Combining qMRI with machine learning enables precise localization of tumors and assessment of disease progression, further enhancing the clinical utility of radiological data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computational single-cell biology</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/single-cell/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/single-cell/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="single-cell-rna-seq">Single-cell RNA-seq&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One research focus of MLO is on the development of application driven probabilistic machine-learning methods for analyzing high-throughput single-cell RNA-seq data.
Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) has become a widely used routine assay and recent scRNA-seq protocols now allow to obtain an unbiased profile of transcriptional heterogeneity at a genome-wide scale, which can be scaled to large datasets with up to millions of cells.
Analysis of such data is challenging: As the intrinsic cellular state of individual cells cannot be directly assayed, cell states need to be inferred from the transcriptional profiling data itself. To this end, single-cell profiling data pose new challenges and opportunities to derive powerful latent variable models (LVMs) that help to exploit large datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="visualization-of-latent-cell-states">Visualization of latent cell states&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We have developed several tools tailored towards inferring and visualizing internal cell states. This includes inferring the internal cell-cycle state of individual cells via Gaussian Process Latent Variabe Models (GPLVM), as well as GPLVM-based identification of cell subpopulations. In addition, we have created tools based on diffusion maps that allow to recover the intrinsic order of cels, e.g. in terms of their differentiation state.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="identification-of-sources-of-cell-cell-variation">Identification of sources of cell-cell variation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Cell-cell variability in terms of gene expression results from a variety of potential sources, including technical noise, biological variation of interest and unwanted biologicl variation (e.g. mitochonrial genes, cell cycle state, etc.). To disentangle these sources of variation, we designed slalom, an interpretable latent variable model that addresses three key tasks in computational scRNA-seq&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Disentagling biological and technical sources of variation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Visualizing the pathways driving cell-cell variation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Refining pathway annotations in an experiment-specific manner&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>