<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Project_news | MLO Lab</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/</link><atom:link href="https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Project_news</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2025 MLO Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:46:01 +0200</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://mlo-lab.github.io/media/logo_huedbb8239ffd36c55e33765ff7c80fb90_78702_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url><title>Project_news</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/</link></image><item><title>Trustworthy Machine Learning in Biomedical Research</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/trustworthy-ml/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:46:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/trustworthy-ml/</guid><description>&lt;p>As machine learning becomes increasingly central to biomedical discovery and clinical decision-making, ensuring the reliability, fairness, and interpretability of these models is critical. In our lab, we are committed to developing and applying machine learning methods that are not only accurate but also &lt;strong>trustworthy&lt;/strong>, meaning they are robust to noise, generalizable across datasets, transparent in their decision-making, and aligned with ethical and clinical standards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our work spans multiple aspects of trustworthy ML, including uncertainty quantification, model calibration, interpretability, fairness in predictive models, and robustness to distributional shifts. These components are especially important in healthcare, where decisions influenced by models can have direct consequences for patients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the context of multi-omics data, single-cell analysis, and quantitative imaging, we embed trustworthiness principles throughout the model development pipeline, from data preprocessing and integration to prediction and interpretation. This ensures that our computational outputs can be confidently used to guide biological insight and translational applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ongoing-projects">Ongoing Projects&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;em>To be completed: This section will describe specific methods, tools, or case studies currently under development in the lab that focus on trustworthy machine learning.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Computational Molecular Medicine</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/single-cell/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:36:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/single-cell/</guid><description>&lt;p>Single-cell multi-omics data present unique challenges: extreme sparsity and technical noise from dropouts, high dimensionality with thousands of features per cell, and pervasive batch and donor effects that can obscure true biological variation. Robust normalization, dimensionality reduction, and noise-modeling approaches are therefore essential to recover reliable signals and ensure that downstream analyses reflect genuine cellular heterogeneity rather than artifacts of the technology. Our lab combines advanced computational methods with high-dimensional biological data to uncover mechanisms of disease, with a particular emphasis on cancer and metabolic disorders. By integrating single-cell multi-omics, and in vivo model data, we aim to build a mechanistic and spatially resolved understanding of disease progression and therapeutic response.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="single-cell-multi-omics-in-clinical-cohorts">Single-Cell Multi-Omics in Clinical Cohorts&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We specialize in the analysis of clinical single-cell multi-omics datasets, particularly from cancer and metabolic disease cohorts. Using state-of-the-art machine learning techniques, we analyze single-cell RNA sequencing and chromatin accessibility data to characterize cellular heterogeneity and regulatory dynamics. Our pipeline includes robust dimensionality reduction, clustering, and batch correction methods, allowing us to identify distinct cell populations and states across individuals. Through probabilistic graphical modeling and motif enrichment analysis, we reconstruct gene regulatory networks that govern disease-specific transcriptional programs. These approaches allow us to overcome the sparsity and noise inherent to single-cell data and extract biologically meaningful patterns that inform prognosis and therapeutic strategy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="multi-omics-in-mouse-models-of-cancer">Multi-Omics in Mouse Models of Cancer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To explore tumor development and treatment effects in vivo, we analyze multi-omics data generated from mouse models, including xenografts and genetically induced cancers. These datasets are complex, encompassing multiple axes of variation such as treatment regimens, time points, and tumor subtypes. To disentangle these factors, we develop tailored probabilistic latent variable models (LVMs) that reveal how sources of variability interact and which molecular features are relevant to human disease. This framework enables us to translate findings from experimental models into clinically actionable insights.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantitative Imaging in Oncology</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/medical-imaging/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:36:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/medical-imaging/</guid><description>&lt;p>High-dimensional imaging datasets pose significant challenges in quantification and interpretation, as traditional analyses often lose critical spatial context and suffer from variability across samples. Our lab applies quantitative imaging, from multiplex confocal microscopy to imaging flow cytometry, to convert biological images into precise, spatially resolved measurements that retain each cell’s location, phenotype, and interactions. We’ve developed colocatome frameworks to map and quantify in situ cellular organization, revealing how microenvironments regulate cell behavior. In parallel, we extract reproducible radiomic features (texture, intensity, shape) and qMRI metrics (e.g., relaxation times) from MRI scans and deploy interpretable machine-learning models to link these imaging biomarkers to clinical outcomes, enabling precise tumor localization and non-invasive monitoring of disease progression.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="quantitative-imaging-and-spatial-analysis">Quantitative Imaging and Spatial Analysis&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We apply quantitative imaging to transform biological images into measurable, interpretable data. From advanced multiplex platforms such as confocal microscopy and imaging flow cytometry, we obtain high-dimensional spatial and phenotypic profiles of cells in their native tissue context. Unlike bulk or sequencing-based approaches, this imaging allows us to retain crucial information on cell location, identity, and interaction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A major component of our spatial analysis pipeline is the development of colocatome frameworks, which quantify the organization and interaction of cell populations in situ. For example, we investigate the spatial positioning of hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) within bone marrow niches using high-resolution microscopy. Understanding these spatial relationships is essential for revealing how microenvironments regulate stem cell behavior and lineage commitment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="radiomics-and-quantitative-mri">Radiomics and Quantitative MRI&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Our imaging research also includes radiological data analysis, with a focus on transitioning from qualitative interpretation to quantitative, reproducible metrics. In radiomics, we extract features such as texture, intensity, and shape from defined regions of interest within MRI scans, and use machine learning models to link these features to clinical outcomes. We emphasize interpretability and robustness, testing models on controlled environments to avoid confounding due to real-patient variability and ethical exposure limitations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In parallel, we employ quantitative MRI (qMRI) techniques to move beyond traditional contrast-based imaging. By measuring intrinsic physical properties of tissues, e.g. relaxation times, we obtain microstructural insights into tissue composition, particularly in brain imaging. Combining qMRI with machine learning enables precise localization of tumors and assessment of disease progression, further enhancing the clinical utility of radiological data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Interpretable Integration of Multi-Omics Data</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/multi-omics/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 22:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project_new/multi-omics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Understanding the complexity of cancer requires making sense of equally complex biological data. In our lab, we develop probabilistic models for the integration of multi-omics datasets, where each patient is described by diverse molecular layers such as genomics, epigenomics, transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics. These models uncover hidden structure in the data by capturing both shared and modality-specific sources of variation. This allows us to reduce noise, infer biologically meaningful patterns, and model system-level responses to perturbations such as drug treatments or environmental changes. Our goal is to produce representations that are not only statistically robust, but also interpretable, resulting in novel biological insights can be directly extracted and validated.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="muvi">MuVI&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>MuVI is a general-purpose probabilistic latent variable model for multi-omics integration that incorporates prior biological knowledge into its structure. It uses pathway annotations, gene sets, or cell-type signatures to guide the discovery of latent factors that explain variation across different data types. Even when this prior knowledge is noisy or incomplete, MuVI is able to learn biologically relevant dimensions, enabling scientists to interpret the sources of variation in the data more clearly and to relate them to known mechanisms.
&lt;img src="muvi.png" alt="MuVI">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="music">MUSIC&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>MUSIC (MUltiview baySIan tensor deComposition) extends probabilistic modeling to high-dimensional array data, such as time-series or condition-specific measurements. It jointly decomposes collections of heterogeneous tensors, e.g. patient × gene × time or patient × protein × condition, into shared and modality-specific components. With structured sparsity priors and efficient variational inference, MUSIC scales to large datasets, handles missing data, and yields interpretable embeddings. We have applied it to cancer drug-response studies and single-cell leukemia data, where it revealed meaningful molecular signatures associated with disease pathways.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="momo-gp">MOMO-GP&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>MOMO-GP (Multi-Omic Multi-output Gaussian Processes) addresses the challenge of learning interpretable representations from single-cell multi-omics data, which are typically high-dimensional, sparse, and nonlinear. Unlike traditional methods that trade off interpretability for modeling power, MOMO-GP combines neural networks with Gaussian Processes to achieve both. It learns separate latent embeddings for cells and features, as well as shared and modality-specific components in the multi-view setting. By modeling gene relevance explicitly, MOMO-GP connects cell clusters to marker genes, making the learned structure readily interpretable in biological terms.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="joana">JOANA&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>JOANA is a probabilistic model for pathway enrichment analysis (PEA) that overcomes limitations of classical approaches like Over-Representation Analysis (ORA) and Functional Class Scoring (FCS). While methods such as GSEA work with continuous scores, they typically operate on a single omics layer and can yield overly broad sets of enriched pathways. JOANA improves on this by modeling enrichment scores across multiple omics layers using mixtures of beta distributions within a Bayesian framework. This allows it to estimate the probability of pathway enrichment both within and across modalities, yielding higher precision and more biologically relevant results.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mofaflex">MOFAFLEX&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>MOFAFLEX is our upcoming framework for flexible and interpretable multi-omics integration. Designed to generalize the principles behind models like MuVI and MUSIC, MOFAFLEX supports heterogeneous data types, modular priors, and scalable inference. Its architecture allows for tailored modeling of real-world datasets, balancing interpretability with modeling flexibility. MOFAFLEX is currently under active development and will provide a unified foundation for future applications in cancer biology and beyond.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>