<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bernhard Hellmann | MLO Lab</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/bernhard-hellmann/</link><atom:link href="https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/bernhard-hellmann/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Bernhard Hellmann</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2026 MLO Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:58:55 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/bernhard-hellmann/avatar_hu02aa61ae1d9de35cbe238d2676170cb9_288892_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Bernhard Hellmann</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/bernhard-hellmann/</link></image><item><title>Insights into FLAME: Visit by Dr. Marius Herr</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/flame-project-herr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:58:55 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/flame-project-herr/</guid><description>&lt;p>We hosted Dr. Marius Herr from the University of Tübingen, who presented FLAME — &lt;a href="https://docs.privateaim.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Federated Learning and Analyses in Medicine&lt;/a>, a platform developed within the privateAIM initiative. He outlined how patient data can be analyzed in a privacy-preserving manner and demonstrated how our methods could be applied to clinical data through FLAME.
The subsequent discussions provided practical insights into the requirements for clinically ready applications of such systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We warmly thank Dr. Herr for his visit and the constructive exchange. We look forward to staying in contact and exploring potential collaborations as FLAME moves toward national implementation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome to our newest team member, Azza</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/azza-welcome-to-the-team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 10:38:11 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/azza-welcome-to-the-team/</guid><description>&lt;p>Azza joins our ML sub-team as a doctoral researcher working on uncertainty quantification and estimation for trustworthy AI. She brings experience in applied machine learning and language model engineering and will support our ongoing research on reliable ML methods in oncology.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Florian named among the world’s most cited researchers — huge congrats to the whole MLO Lab team!</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/buettner-most-cited-2025/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 14:41:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/buettner-most-cited-2025/</guid><description>&lt;p>A proud moment: Florian has been listed as a Highly Cited Researcher 2025, placing him among the top 1% of scientists worldwide. This recognition reflects the shared work, ideas, and energy that move our lab forward every day. Proud to have this team! &lt;a href="https://aktuelles.uni-frankfurt.de/en/english/seven-goethe-university-researchers-among-the-most-cited-scientists-in-the-world/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Official Announcement&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome to our newest team member, Rashika</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/rashika-welcome-to-the-team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:43:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/rashika-welcome-to-the-team/</guid><description>&lt;p>Rashika joins the MLO Lab as a doctoral researcher working on probabilistic machine learning for multi-omic data integration and foundation-model approaches for single-cell representation learning. She will contribute to our research on machine learning methods for cancer data analysis.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome to the team, Hendrik</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/hendrik-welcome-to-the-team/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 09:29:04 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/hendrik-welcome-to-the-team/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hendrik joins our ML sub-team, working on machine learning methods that combine large-scale EHR data with other data types such as genomics. He focuses on causality and uncertainty estimation and will support our ongoing methodological work.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>