<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Arber Qoku | MLO Lab</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/</link><atom:link href="https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Arber Qoku</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 MLO Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 16:54:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/avatar_hu8fde1aa7751d583fe1478cbaeb1ab1ed_971266_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Arber Qoku</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/</link></image><item><title>MuVI</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/muvi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 16:54:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/muvi/</guid><description>&lt;p>Many real-world systems are described not only by data from a single source but via multiple data views. In genomic medicine, for instance, a patient can be described by data from different molecular layers. This raises the need for multi-view models that are able to disentangle variation within and across data views in an interpretable manner. Latent variable models with structured sparsity are a commonly used tool to address this modeling task but interpretability is cumbersome since it requires a direct inspection and interpretation of each factor via a specialized domain expert. Here, we propose MuVI, a novel approach for domain-informed multi-view latent variable models, facilitating the analysis of multi-view data in an inherently explainable manner. We demonstrate that our model (i) is able to integrate noisy domain expertise in from of feature sets, (ii) is robust to noise in the encoded domain knowledge, (iii) results in identifiable factors and (iv) is able to infer interpretable and biologically meaningful axes of variation in real-world multi-view datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Get started right away with &lt;a href="https://github.com/MLO-lab/MuVI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MuVI&lt;/a>!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open Position: R Package for Multi-omics Data Integration</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/open-position-muvi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 19:51:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/open-position-muvi/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are looking for a motivated student with excellent skills in R to join a collaborative project for developing an open source software to support the analysis of multi-omics data. Our recently developed Bayesian approach for modelling multi-view data by integrating domain expertise (MuVI) is currently only supported in Python. The goal of the project is to further develop the MuVI framework and extend its functionality into an R package. You will work closely with other team members, and participate regularly in group dicussions. The work schedule is very flexible. Note that this position may also be fully remote.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your responsibilities:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Writing clean, maintainable and well-documented code.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Developing a reticulate interface to facilitate interoperability between Python and R.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Developing an R package according to the Bioconductor principles and guidelines.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Participating actively in group meetings.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Requirements:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Currently enrolled in a German university and are studying informatics, bioinformatics, mathematics, physics or related.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Experienced in R, and have a basic understanding of developing packages in R.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Basic knowledge in Python (preferred).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proficient in written and spoken English.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Click on the project link above and take a look at our GitHub repository!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have any questions or would like to submit an application, use our &lt;a href="../../#contact">contact form&lt;/a> and send us an email with a short introduction and your CV.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paper accepted at KDD 2021!</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/spexlvm-kdd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 16:30:04 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/spexlvm-kdd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Latent variable models are powerful statistical tools that can uncover relevant variation between patients or cells, by inferring unobserved hidden states from observable high-dimensional data. A major shortcoming of current methods, however, is their inability to learn sparse and interpretable hidden states. Additionally, in settings where partial knowledge on the latent structure of the data is readily available, a statistically sound integration of prior information into current methods is challenging. To address these issues, we propose spex-LVM, a factorial latent variable model with &lt;strong>s&lt;/strong>parse &lt;strong>p&lt;/strong>riors to encourage the inference of &lt;strong>ex&lt;/strong>plainable factors driven by domain-relevant information. spex-LVM utilizes existing knowledge of curated biomedical pathways to automatically assign annotated attributes to latent factors, yielding interpretable results tailored to the corresponding domain of interest. Evaluations on simulated and real single-cell RNA-seq datasets demonstrate that our model robustly identifies relevant structure in an inherently explainable manner, distinguishes technical noise from sources of biomedical variation, and provides data-driven adaptations of existing pathway annotations.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>