<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Arber Qoku | MLO Lab</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/</link><atom:link href="https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Arber Qoku</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2025 MLO Lab</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 22:16:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/avatar_hu8fde1aa7751d583fe1478cbaeb1ab1ed_971266_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url><title>Arber Qoku</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/author/arber-qoku/</link></image><item><title>Paper accepted at ICML CompBio 2023!</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/qoku-cellij-icml-23/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 22:16:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/qoku-cellij-icml-23/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper accepted! Our latest work on developing a versatile framework for rapid prototyping and training of a wide range of factor analysis models for multi-omics data got accepted at this year&amp;rsquo;s ICML workshop on computational biology!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paper accepted at AISTATS 2023!</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/qoku-encoding-aistats-23/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 16:15:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/qoku-encoding-aistats-23/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper accepted! Our latest work on multi-view latent variable models with structured sparsity got accepted at this year&amp;rsquo;s AISTATS conference!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Encoding domain knowledge in multi-view latent variable models: A bayesian approach with structured sparsity</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/publication/qoku-2023-encoding/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/publication/qoku-2023-encoding/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Multimodal analysis methods in predictive biomedicine</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/publication/qoku-2023-multimodal/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/publication/qoku-2023-multimodal/</guid><description/></item><item><title>MuVI</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/muvi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 16:54:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/project/muvi/</guid><description>&lt;p>Many real-world systems are described not only by data from a single source but via multiple data views. In genomic medicine, for instance, a patient can be described by data from different molecular layers. This raises the need for multi-view models that are able to disentangle variation within and across data views in an interpretable manner. Latent variable models with structured sparsity are a commonly used tool to address this modeling task but interpretability is cumbersome since it requires a direct inspection and interpretation of each factor via a specialized domain expert. Here, we propose MuVI, a novel approach for domain-informed multi-view latent variable models, facilitating the analysis of multi-view data in an inherently explainable manner. We demonstrate that our model (i) is able to integrate noisy domain expertise in from of feature sets, (ii) is robust to noise in the encoded domain knowledge, (iii) results in identifiable factors and (iv) is able to infer interpretable and biologically meaningful axes of variation in real-world multi-view datasets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Get started right away with &lt;a href="https://github.com/MLO-lab/MuVI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MuVI&lt;/a>!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paper accepted at KDD 2021!</title><link>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/spexlvm-kdd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 16:30:04 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://mlo-lab.github.io/post/spexlvm-kdd/</guid><description>&lt;p>Latent variable models are powerful statistical tools that can uncover relevant variation between patients or cells, by inferring unobserved hidden states from observable high-dimensional data. A major shortcoming of current methods, however, is their inability to learn sparse and interpretable hidden states. Additionally, in settings where partial knowledge on the latent structure of the data is readily available, a statistically sound integration of prior information into current methods is challenging. To address these issues, we propose spex-LVM, a factorial latent variable model with &lt;strong>s&lt;/strong>parse &lt;strong>p&lt;/strong>riors to encourage the inference of &lt;strong>ex&lt;/strong>plainable factors driven by domain-relevant information. spex-LVM utilizes existing knowledge of curated biomedical pathways to automatically assign annotated attributes to latent factors, yielding interpretable results tailored to the corresponding domain of interest. Evaluations on simulated and real single-cell RNA-seq datasets demonstrate that our model robustly identifies relevant structure in an inherently explainable manner, distinguishes technical noise from sources of biomedical variation, and provides data-driven adaptations of existing pathway annotations.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>